Guide to the Miscellaneous French Documents, 1781-1918
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Miscellaneous French Documents 1781-1918
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
0.1 linear feet Extent: 15 Items
Collection contains fourteen French documents written between the 18th century and the 20th century. The contents of these documents are broad in scope from sales accounts to personal letters to official government documents. Of note are several documents that refer to American cities such as Augusta, Baltimore, Philadelphia, and Savannah. Several of the documents are written by or are addressed to fairly prominent historical figures: British Ambassador Charles Stuart, Minister of the Interior Alexandre-Auguste Ledru Rollin, General Joseph Léopold Sigisbert (Hugo), and Cardinal Jean-Sifrein Maury.
RL.00899
Language: Material in French
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Miscellaneous French Documents were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift prior to 1942.
Collection Overview
Collection contains fourteen French documents written between the 18th century and the 20th century. The contents of these documents are broad in scope from sales accounts to personal letters to official government documents. Of note are several documents that refer to American cities such as Augusta, Baltimore, Philadelphia, and Savannah. Several of the documents are written by or are addressed to fairly prominent historical figures: British Ambassador Charles Stuart, Minister of the Interior Alexandre-Auguste Ledru Rollin, General Joseph Léopold Sigisbert (Hugo), and Cardinal Jean-Sifrein Maury.
Subject Headings
Hugo, Joseph-Léopold-Sigisbert, comte, 1773-1828; Ledru-Rollin, 1807-1874; Maury, Jean Siffrein, 1746-1817; France -- History -- 18th century; France -- History -- 19th century; France -- Politics and government -- 18th century
Contents of Collection
- Miscellaneous French Documents, 1781-1918, (1 folder)
  - General Joseph Léopold Sigisbert (Hugo), 1798 July 14 (26 Messidor, l'an 6) (Folder 1)
    This is the personal stationary of Joseph Léopold Sigisbert (Hugo) who was the father of Victor Hugo. The header features a French Republic crest between two words: Liberté and Egalité. This is a handwritten note in black ink on letterhead from the 1st Permanent War Council of the 17th Military Division for the French Government. Written during the French Revolution, the document is dated as 26 Messidor, l'an 6 (July 14th, 1798).
  - List of fabrics and prices, 1781 (Folder 1)
    This document, handwritten in black ink and dated 1781, is an itemized list of fabrics (including wool blankets) and appears to be for someone named Terrasson. The verso includes a reference to Baltimore in the header and there are instructions to purchase the aforementioned items and send them to a residence in Alexandria.
  - Letter from Maury (possibly Cardinal Jean-Sifrein Maury) in reference to Auguste Charles Brice and his marriage, 1795 April 23 (Folder 1)
  - Letter from Maury (possibly Cardinal Jean-Sifrein Maury) in reference to Auguste Charles Brice and his marriage, 1795 April 26 (Folder 1)
  - Notary document signed by Alex Parain referring to Auguste Charles Brice and his marriage, circa 1802 January 18 (Folder 1)
  - Letter signed by "Bach," 1784-1785 (Folder 1)
    Letter refers to a shipment en route to Philadelphia.
  - Letter from Pindardi to Mr. Dugas (a merchant in Augusta, Ga.), 1836 January 6 (Folder 1)
    Beginning with the words 'Mon Cher Monsieur' (My Dear Sir), it is written by someone named Pindardi and is addressed to a Mr. Dugas (Merchant) in Augusta. This is probably a reference to the city in Georgia, as Savannah is also mentioned. The letter appears to be sent from Clarksville.
  - To do list for trip to St. Maler, undated (Folder 1)
    This item appears to be a to-do list for someone going to St. Maler. The document consists of notes on the verso and eight points on the recto which concern a family named Dedieu (Louis Dedieu in particular) making reference to several things such as baptism, parental rights, and verifying whether the Louis Dedieu in question is the same one who made a fortune in St. Dominique.
  - Note addressed to Mr. Terrasson, undated (Folder 1)
    A brief note addressed to Mr. Terrasson, signed by Sicard (possibly Père Claude Sicard) referring to money.
  - Account statement of Jean Terrasson de Lyon, 1782 (Folder 1)
    One-page statement for a sales account, possibly from 1782, of 'Jean Terrasson de Lyon' and details the 'net merchandise products' (e.g. white satin) on board an American ship and includes the identifier 'TFC No.2'. There are also instructions for where these materials should be sent.
  - Letter to British Ambassador (possibly Charles Stuart), 1818, December 20 (Folder 1)
    One page note written to the British Ambassador (possibly Charles Stuart); appears to be signed by someone named 'Ledru'. This note is to inform the Ambassador that a Madame Suller will be presented to the King the following day at 8 o'clock at night.
  - Letter from Ledru-Rollin, 1868 February 25 (Folder 1)
    One page letter written on the letterhead of the Cabinet of the Minister of the Interior (Cabinet du Ministre de l'Interieur) and signed by Alexandre-Auguste Ledru Rollin (possibly written while in exile in England). It pertains to communication with the government.
  - Letter to Moucher, 1881 April 16 (Folder 1)
    Single page note with a black border appears to be addressed to someone named Moucher and refers to something "terrible" regarding the whereabouts of a ticket.
  - Form letter regarding conditions for release of a German prisoner, 1918 December 1 (Folder 1)
    This form letter from the "Xe Armée État-Major 2e Buereau' on behalf of the President of the Triage Commission. Composed just after the end of the First World War, the letter details the conditions for release of a German prisoner (the name of the German soldier appears to be Joseph Molimann). In bold script there are instructions for the German soldier to immediately leave the German army, or he will face the French Military Authorities.
  - Partially printed invitation card from Russian Ambassador to Comte Joseph Attems. (Folder 1)